All right well he doesn't discuss this he questioned one of their
ערווה. Erva. Anyway, so again we're again bottom of י"ט עמוד ב'
Yud Tes Amud Beis and the discussion here is about the issue
of human dignity and how much that has an impact in terms
of עבירות Averas to override certain concerns and the גמרא Gemara's basic
position is it does not override a biblical concern like wearing כלאים
Kilayim but we have now and there were some evidence that maybe
it did about טומאה Tuma but it managed to put that aside
and say that was only rabbinic
and a rabbinic concern it would override and then in the end
we ended with the example about not having to return a lost
object which is biblical and it's a positive מצוה Mitzvah not a
violation but it's the lack of performance of a positive מצוה Mitzvah
might be a violation there's a negative prohibition about do not hide
your eyes from it do not abandon the אבידה Aveida and there
the גמרא Gemara says yes that's true there that principle is in
effect a person does not have to return a lost object if
it's beneath his dignity to bend down and pick it up but
that's an issue about a monetary issue and therefore the standards are
different than when you're directly confronting a prohibition and now the גמרא
Gemara wraps this up or whatever asks one final question before coming
to a conclusion so we pick up again at the bottom of
י"ט עמוד ב' Yud Tes Amud Beis and we say the following
thank you it says תא שמע Tashma one two about six lines
from the bottom come and hear ולאחותו Velaachoso
this is about a נזיר Nazir cannot become טמא Tamei to his
anybody who dies even an immediate family member like a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and it says to his sister he cannot become טמא
Tamei מה תלמוד לומר Mah Talmud Lomar why does it have to
say he can't become טמא Tamei to his sister it already said
he cannot become טמא Tamei impure to his mother or father if
they die so to tell you that there's even another case that
you might think it says to tell the following case שהיה הולך
לשחוט את פסחו ולמול את בנו ושמע שמת לו מת Shehaya holech
lishchot es pishcho velamul es beno veshama shemeis lo meis let's say
somebody was going and even this נזיר Nazir and he was going
to שחט shecht his קרבן פסח Korban Pesach or to give a
ברית מילה Bris Milah to his son and he heard and if
he says that an immediate family member died יכול יחזור ויטמא Yachol
yachzor veyitameh
maybe he should go and become טמא Tamei אמרת לא יטמא Amarta
Lo Yitameh
okay so he cannot become טמא Tamei now that's pretty obvious he
can't become טמא Tamei to a family member how much more so
can you not become טמא Tamei when there's all these other reasons
not to become טמא Tamei like he has to bring a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach if he becomes טמא Tamei he won't be able
to bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach he has to do a
ברית מילה Bris Milah now there exactly becoming טמא Tamei doesn't get
in the way of doing a ברית מילה Bris Milah but somehow
maybe that'll prevent him from doing this ברית מילה Bris Milah just
the time that it takes not the becoming טמא Tamei so obviously
he can't become טמא Tamei in those cases I mean there's even
more reasons not to so the חידוש Chidush is not that he
can't become טמא Tamei the חידוש Chidush is the exception of when
he is allowed to become טמא Tamei and that's the next line
יכול Yachol it says okay לא יטמא Lo Yitameh יכול כשם שאינו
מיטמא להם כך אינו מיטמא למת מצוה Yachol kesheim sheino mitameh lahem
kach eino mitameh lemeis mitzvah
maybe the same way he cannot become טמא Tamei to immediate family
members he can also not become טמא Tamei to a מת מצוה
Meis Mitzvah somebody who died and there is nobody to bury him
so that person who is urgently in need of somebody to bury
him and there's nobody else around that is a category that is
not anywhere explicit in the תורה Torah but the rabbis basically identified
this category and this is here the תורה Torah says a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol cannot become טמא Tamei to immediate family members a
נזיר Nazir cannot become טמא Tamei to immediate family members cannot bury
them but the rabbis says oh but that's always if somebody else
is around to bury them but if nobody is around to bury
them then not only immediate family members but if there's somebody there
dead and he's not being taken care of that overrides everything it
even overrides a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol overrides a נזיר Nazir you
violate everything to take not everything but you violate טומאה Tuma in
order to take care of this מת מצוה Meis Mitzvah so first
of all again that's no in the פסוקים Pesukim but that's what
the rabbis understand and read in and here they're reading it in
for this case of the נזיר Nazir and they're going further and
they're saying even if this guy's a נזיר Nazir and not only
is he gonna override his נזירות Nezirut to become טמא Tamei to
this person who has nobody around to bury a מת מצוה Meis
Mitzvah but he's a נזיר Nazir and he's on his way to
bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and he's on his way to
give a ברית מילה Bris Milah to his son and he has
all these other things that would dictate not to become טמא Tamei
taking care of the מת מצוה Meis Mitzvah overrides yes
but he still wouldn't violate שבת Shabbos
he wouldn't violate שבת Shabbos so there's some
things you override some you don't
right exactly and it's specifically טומאה Tuma correct and that's a point
we'll get to in a minute so okay so how maybe I
would think he would not תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar ולאחותו Velaachoso that's
what the extra word ולאחותו Velaachoso tells you ולאחותו הוא שאינו מיטמא
Velaachoso hu sheino mitameh he's only for his sister he doesn't become
טמא Tamei no no he doesn't become טמא Tamei to his father
but to tell me okay these are the people he doesn't become
טמא Tamei to his relatives אבל מיטמא הוא למת מצוה Aval mitameh
hu lemeis mitzvah he does become טמא Tamei
דף כ' עמוד א' Daf Chof Amud Aleph to a מת מצוה
Meis Mitzvah somebody who is dead and there is nobody to bury
so here we have a general principle that and another ברייתא Braisa
also whatever earlier in the ברייתא Braisa adds not only that if
he's also let's say a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has all these
other reasons why he would not become טמא Tamei it all gets
overridden for the sake of a מת מצוה. Meis Mitzvah. Okay so
now we have says since we have a principle that מת מצווה
meis mitzvah presumably the dictating mandate there right is the issue of
כבוד הבריות. kvod habriyos. Because what makes that מת מצווה meis mitzvah
question different than other מצוות, mitzvos, what where is that urgency coming
from the מת מצווה meis mitzvah that does not apply to his
dead father? Forget there is somebody to bury. Can't just be the
abstract מצוה, mitzvah, the urgency has to be coming from an aspect
of כבוד הבריות, kvod habriyos, which is by the way quite fascinating
if you think about the juxtaposition right. We're talking about כבוד הבריות,
kvod habriyos, we were talking about כבוד הרב kvod harav after having
the previous סוגיא sugya discussing you know that the the implications of
not being respectful to כבוד הרב kvod harav and being put into
a type of a נידוי nidui of an excommunication, how weighty כבוד
הרב kvod harav is. We have an earlier discussion also about כבוד
המת kvod hameis right and about that a person cannot involve himself
in מצוות mitzvos if he just suffered a loss he has to
involve all of his head space into the dead body, being שומר
המת, shomer hameis, all these things around כבוד המת. kvod hameis. And
here the question is okay so what is the weight of those
things and here we say it doesn't override a negative prohibition. So
אמאי amai why is that true? לימא אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין
עצה לנגד השם. leima ein chochma ve'ein tevuna ve'ein eitza leneged Hashem.
Why don't we say there's no חכמה chochma when it comes to
מצוה mitzvah when it comes to you know violating God's command. Who
cares if it's a כבוד הבריות kvod habriyos issue you don't violate
the command not to become טמא. tamei. So you see that when
there's an urgent issue of human dignity then it does override. גמרא
Gemara says no, שאני התם דכתיב ולאחותו. shani hatam dechsiv velachoso. That's
an exception. It has a special פסוק pasuk ולאחותו velachoso there's a
special category of מת מצווה meis mitzvah that overrides טומאה tumah and
that's an exception there and it's and you know it's a one-case
exception. So גמרא Gemara says well what makes it a one-case exception?
וליגמר מיניה. veligmar minei. רש"י Rashi says why don't we just say
that it overrides all מצוות? mitzvos? Okay which is also a question
you could ask. If the principle is human dignity overrides biblical מצוות,
mitzvos, so maybe it should not just override טומאה tumah it should
override everything. Or maybe we should always say that human dignity overrides
and not just מת מצווה, meis mitzvah, all aspects of human dignity
override. So then it becomes a pretty huge category. So that's גמרא
Gemara saying but how do you know not to use that as
a paradigm? גמרא Gemara says שב ואל תעשה שאני. shev ve'al ta'aseh
shani. Passive is different. Now what the heck answer is that passive
is different? Who's being passive here? Here you're actively violating your טומאה.
tumah. What do you mean being passive is different? So רש"י Rashi
says the following. רש"י Rashi says what this means is is that
sort of skirts the question. רש"י Rashi says we're not really there
saying that we're overriding טומאה tumah for the sake of human dignity.
What we're really saying is is that the prohibitions for a כהן
kohein or נזיר nazir to become טמא tamei were not said when
there was a when the issue of מת מצווה meis mitzvah was
involved. It's sort of like from the very beginning טומאה tumah it's
not like you're violating your prohibition but it's allowed for the sake
of a מת מצווה. meis mitzvah. It's like the תורה Torah from
the very beginning never said that it was forbidden in this case.
Now that in general is a question often phrased as הותרה או
דחויה. hutra o dechuya. Like when I do a violate שבת shabbos
to save a well what I know but let's use the שבת.
shabbos. When I violate שבת shabbos to save somebody who's dying. Do
I treat it as I violated שבת shabbos but I was supposed
to violate שבת shabbos I did a מצוה mitzvah because I have
this מצוה mitzvah I have an obligation to do it but at
the end of the day if you ask what was my act
it was a violation of שבת shabbos but a mandated violation. Or
do you say no there was no violation of שבת shabbos in
the context of saving a person it's not considered a violation at
all. So that's in general a question that you have sometimes with
these issues of overrides. That's what רש"י Rashi what? הותרה או דחויה.
hutra o dechuya.
Not טומאה tumah but הותרה או דחויה hutra o dechuya right. If
it's הותרה hutra like it's permitted it's not even a violation or
no it's violating but it's overridden because of a greater concern. Okay
so it's pushed away as opposed to not forbidden as opposed to
permitted.
Now that's what רש"י Rashi tries to say. Just says you can't
use this as a proof that it overrides because in this case
we're going to frame it as it was never forbidden. Okay. It
might be that טומאה tumah was never forbidden says רש"י. Rashi. But
the fact is you're becoming טמא tamei you're not bringing a
קרבן פסח. korban pesach. You're becoming טמא tamei you're not doing ברית
מילה bris milah for your kid right and those are important מצוות
mitzvos there's כרת kareis associated with them and so on. So there
what so there you can't say it's like פסח pesach was never
said it's like it doesn't work to say the prohibition of טומאה
tumah which is standing in the way of you burying this person
doesn't apply in that case. But the reality still is because of
your doing this thing indirectly you're not being able now to bring
your קרבן פסח. korban pesach. What happened to that? So there רש"י
Rashi says that's the answer of גמרא Gemara you're passive. You're only
passively not observing a מצוה mitzvah and it's a positive מצוה mitzvah
right that you're not observing not negative. Only passively that human dignity
would override. So according to that the conclusion of גמרא Gemara very
important is the following. What does human dignity override? It overrides number
one rabbinic prohibitions and this comes up in other places like for
example here's an example that somebody's out in the field on שבת
shabbos going to the bathroom because you know they didn't have whatever
indoor plumbing and picking up stones and using it as toilet paper
because of an issue of human dignity you know about wiping yourself
and so on. Becomes nowadays you find yourself in the bathroom and
there'll be a supply of toilet paper before שבת. shabbos. So human
dignity overrides. It overrides rabbinic prohibitions. It overrides certainly in that situation,
that's a שב ואל תעשה.
shev v'al taaseh. No, that's a קום ועשה, kum va'aseh, but it's
rabbinic. So even active violation of rabbinic prohibitions, okay, like the גמרא
Gemara about becoming טמא tamei for, you know, cases where it's rabbinic
טומאה. tumah. It overrides certain monetary issues like returning an אבידה, aveidah,
exactly what the parameters of those are, doesn't mean you can steal
something from somebody to be, you know, but in terms of certain
monetary sort of obligations, presumably like more, you know, מצוות mitzvos related
obligations. It overrides and presumably overrides even biblical מצוות mitzvos if it's
passive non-performance as opposed to active violation. Give me an example of
a passive non-performance.
I don't know, let's say מצות תקיעת שופר mitzvas tekias shofar that
if you created some scenario where in order for me to go
do the מצוה mitzvah of תקיעת שופר tekias shofar would be a
profound issue of, you know, human dignity here. I don't know, let's
say, I mean, that then raises another question of how do you
exactly define the parameters of dignity? What does dignity mean? What's a
case of dignity? But I don't know, let's say there's an example
that, you know, who knows? Your clothes were ripped from you, you
would have to be walking naked in the street, you need me
there to protect you and walk you home or whatever, and it's
going to miss תקיעת שופר. tekias shofar. Okay? So I would have
to take care of, or me myself, and what I would have
to do to protect my dignity, but it means I'm going to
have to, you know, avoid going into שול shul and miss תקיעת
שופר. tekias shofar. Okay? So a passive non-performance of would be also
even of a biblical would override. Now that becomes a very fascinating
question because, you know, how broadly or narrowly do you define human
dignity, how often do you invoke this principle, which sort of comes
from the outside and interrupts things? And there's a real question about
how much פוסקים poskim use issues of כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos in
their תשובות. teshuvos. Actually, many years ago, at an Edah conference, Rabbi
Ezra Labaton gave a שיעור shiur on like the use of כבוד
הבריות kevod habriyos in Sephardic פסק. psak. And it seems at least
his contention was that in Sephardic פסק, psak, כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos
as this sort of override within the parameters the גמרא Gemara gives
is much more prevalent in Sephardic פסק psak than it is in
Ashkenazic, which is interesting. I don't know about that or not. Dov,
do you have a sense of that? Wait. Yes.
It's so subjective
how to define parameters of what defines dignity. Yes.
There's no way you can.
Yes, but you could still ask questions, you know, does dignity mean
about other people seeing you in a certain way? Does it mean
your own sense of, I mean, you're right, you can never fully
objectify but you can try to put some type of, you know,
guidelines to what defines dignity. But yes.
And as such, it really, I think it broaches the question of
how do you value the מצוה? mitzvah? Yeah. At the end of
the day, or why not one, you know? What are the relative
relative values?
Right. So I mean, that's why and I think that's probably why
פוסקים poskim will are probably more reluctant to use it because it's
so amorphous and interpreted in some ways it could, you know, every
single thing, כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyos, כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyos, כבוד הבריות,
kevod habriyos, you know? But on the other hand, if you're so
afraid of it, then it's not doing the job it's supposed to
be doing. But yeah, I agree that's part of the issue, yes.
I think it's important to clarify by מת מצוה meis mitzvah whose
כבוד kevod we're concerned about. Yes. Are we saying כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyos because it's not nice that a dead body is out?
So that's why I mentioned the issue. Right. So that's why I
mentioned, you know, the גמרא Gemara does seem, especially the whole category
of אונן onen as ירושלמי Yerushalmi understands it, is an issue of
כבוד kevod for the מת. meis. And that does then raise that
issue, you know, about מתים אינם יודעים מאומה. meisim einam yodim m'umah.
What does כבוד kevod for a מת meis mean? You know, is
כבוד kevod for the מת meis indirectly really a type of כבוד
kevod of society of how we're treating our מתים? meisim? You know,
how to conceptualize the idea of כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos for a
מת? meis? But again, it is something that the גמרא Gemara seems
to somewhat be taking for granted. The גמרא's Gemara not problematizing the
question of how can you talk about כבוד kevod of a dead
person? He's dead. Right? It sort of asks the question did the
dead know anything, but in sense of that there's a sense of
כבוד kevod shown to them, many גמרות Gemaros sort of assume that
that's a reasonable concept to talk about, about are we respectful of
their honor or not.
But if we look at it as כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyos, so
it has more room.
I understand. You could try to interpret that that it's a כבוד
kevod about how other people are feeling that there is this dead
body. But you don't get that sense. I don't know. Let's say
I am taking a walk, you know, out in the middle of
nowhere and I'm walking through a forest and I see a dead
body. Nobody in the whole universe knows about it but me. It's
a כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos issue and I still become טמא tamei
to it. No other society's impacted, you know?
And it's my כבוד, kevod, my sense...
Okay, maybe again, that's the problem about, I understand, it is this
problem about how big and amorphous these categories can be.
Okay, let's just start all over again and... Yes, another טומאה tumah
would start all over...
and just one last thing and then we'll continue. תוספות Tosafos doesn't
like רש"י's Rashi claim that, oh, it's not really that it's violating
in this case because, you know, it's like never prohibited. You know,
he says you can always say that and then, whatever. So anyway,
so תוספות Tosafos says that the reason really is, although the גמרא
Gemara doesn't give this as a direct answer, that נזיר nazir and
כהן, kohen, those are all sort of like not universal prohibitions. They
only apply to a כהן, kohen, only apply to a נזיר, nazir,
and
therefore... You cannot be served as a paradigm as opposed to רש"י's
Rashi's answer which it's like הותרה hutra versus דחויה. dchuya. One last
interesting point which actually is very relevant is the question comes up:
what if I find that I'm wearing שעטנז, shaatnez, but I see
that you're wearing שעטנז? shaatnez? And now, if I don't tell you,
you will only violate passively, right? So maybe, and not only passively,
you only violate not willingly, not במזיד, b'meizid, but בשוגג. b'shogeg. So
in the case of the גמרא, Gemara, you are aware, so if
I were to continue to wear it, I am now willfully violating,
and it's not considered passive because the continued wearing is like an
act of wearing, and it's violating a negative prohibition again as opposed
to just passively not doing the מצוה mitzvah of פסח Pesach or
the מצוה mitzvah of מילה, milah, which is lack of performance of
a positive. Here it's active even if it's just standing still, it's
active in the sense it's considered actively wearing. But if I see
you're doing it and you're in ignorance, what is my obligation to
tell
you, and is that a כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos issue? And this
is a big question. There's a famous תשובה teshuva of the נודע
ביהודה Noda BiYehuda where, if I'm remembering correctly, the question was, somebody
said that he knows that a certain woman
committed adultery. Now if the husband were to find out, she would
be forbidden to her husband. Okay? But the husband doesn't know now.
What is his obligation to tell the husband? Right? Because maybe it's
a כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos issue for her, for him, whatever. So
just keep quiet. It's a
כבוד הבריות. kavod habriyos. Is it an active violation? Maybe, but it's
בשוגג. b'shogeg. The גמרא's Gemara case was when you're knowingly violating. Maybe
if you're passively violating I should just keep quiet. Then anyway there's
other questions about even if I told the husband, maybe the husband
wouldn't have to believe me. Okay? But that becomes a fascinating question.
What is my obligation to tell somebody who's in ignorance? Or maybe
I should just let matters be if it's a כבוד הבריות kavod
habriyos even if it's an issue of a prohibition.
Wait, but I have to
check this out.
Okay, I'll check that in the גמרא. Gemara.
I can't
give you his answer from memory because it's not going to be
nuanced or correct. I'll come back to you tomorrow. Okay, let's keep
on going.
I'll have to get back to you about that.
Yeah,
really, we're talking בריה briya here means human. Yes. Sometimes בריה briya
means any creature.
Right. It's like, well, there's also the צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei
chayim, but sometimes בריה, briya, right, does. Especially, right, right. Yeah,
I don't think anybody applies this to animal dignity. But the צער,
tza'ar, but interestingly, now that you mention it, I should point out,
and this is maybe the final thing I'll end with about this
point, that this גמרא Gemara is very strange. It says there's a
principle כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos override דרבנן d'rabanan passive non-performance of positive
מצוות. mitzvos. Where do we know it from? What פסוק pasuk tells
me that there's a מצוה mitzvah of כבוד הבריות? kavod habriyos? What
פסוק pasuk tells me it overrides? The only quasi-source was either the
paradigm of השב תשיבם hashevashiva which the גמרא Gemara bracketed, or the
case about not returning a lost object. Okay? Where there it says
specifically that applies by ממונא. mamona. But all essentially, what we know
that there's this value of כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos is learned out
implicitly from these exceptions of these מצוות. mitzvos. There's never a מצוה
mitzvah that says you have to attend to כבוד הבריות. kavod habriyos.
Well, interestingly, there's one other, and then winds up so this value
then becomes a halakhic principle that plays a role with a direct
role in the halakhic system. There's one other case I know of
where the גמרא Gemara does this, which is it identifies a value
implicit in a מצוה mitzvah and then makes it sort of an
active principle,
a direct halakhic principle, not just a value concern. And that is,
as Dov mentions, it's the issue about צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei
chayim. צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, the גמרא's Gemara a question,
is it דאורייתא d'oraissa or דרבנן? d'rabanan? Even if it's דאורייתא, d'oraissa,
it never says, here's a פסוק pasuk that says you have to
care about צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. The way we know
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is דאורייתא d'oraissa is that it's
the implicit value in certain מצוות, mitzvos, presumably by the way, the
מצוה mitzvah about, well, the one the גמרא Gemara focus on in
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia unloading the animal that's struggling under its load,
and so on. Okay? And then what it does is it says,
if we do have this value and do identify this as a
biblical value and extract it, the role it's going to play is
that צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim overrides rabbinic prohibitions, exactly the
role that כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos plays, overrides rabbinic prohibitions. Okay? So
actually, it's interesting that Dov mentions it, because as far as I
know, those are the only two examples in ש"ס Shas where the
גמרא Gemara identifies a value implicit in a מצוה, mitzvah, extracts it,
and makes it an active sort of factor within הלכה halakha and
something that actually plays has weight, direct weight within sort of halakhic
issues to the effect that at least here it overrides דרבנן d'rabanan
and maybe even non-performance of דאורייתא. d'oraissa. Okay? So now we go
on. That was a really nice sort of halakhic and very central
סוגיא. sugya. Now let's take back to where the גמרא Gemara goes
to the next sort of more aggadic discussion here in the גמרא.
Gemara. So four lines down on כ' עמוד א'. Kaf Amud Aleph.
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye. רב פפא
Rav Pappa said to אביי: Abaye: מאי שנא ראשונים דאיתרחיש להו ניסא
ומאי שנא אנן דלא מיתרחיש לן ניסא. Mai shna rishonim de-itrachish lehu
nisa u-mai shna anan de-lo mitrachish lan nisa. So it's not exactly
clear how this is relevant for anything, we'll see in a minute,
but he said to אביי, Abaye, why was it that the early
sages miracles were performed for them, but for us miracles are not
performed? אי
משום תנויי, Im mishum tanuye, if it's because of learning, that maybe
they were bigger תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim than we were, they knew
more תורה Torah than we did, so בשני דרב יהודה כולי תנויי
בנזיקין הוה. bishnei de-Rav Yehuda kulei tanuye bi-nezikin havei. In the days
of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, who were the earlier אמוראים Amoraim which
he's comparing himself to, all of their knowledge was in נזיקין, Nezikin,
that was really the one section of ש"ס Shas they knew was
נזיקין, Nezikin, and they didn't really study so much the other sections,
certainly not in depth. ואנן קא מתנינן שיתא סדרי. Ve-anan kamasnina shisha
sidrei. We learn all ש"ס, Shas, right? ששה סדרי ש"ס. Shisha Sidrei
Shas. We learn the whole six, all the six orders. We know
we learn it all, משניות Mishnayos and we have in-depth discussions. We
have more greater תורה Torah knowledge than they did. וכי הוה מטי
רב יהודה בעוקצין, Ve-ki havay mati Rav Yehuda be-Uktzin, and here's an
example, when רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, who is the one we're using
as the earlier generation, when he would get up
to עוקצין, Uktzin, which would clearly be the hardest and the most
obscure מסכתא Masecheta of טהרות, Taharos, and Michael is right, it comes
up in other places. And here was the משנה Mishnah he saw:
האישה שוכבשת ירק בקדרה, Ha-ishah she-koveshes yerech bi-kdeirah, a woman who is
pickling, I guess כובשת, koveshes,
a vegetable in a pot. ואמרי לה זיתים שכבשן בטרפיהן, Ve-amreilah zeisim
she-kipsham be-tarfaihem, or olives that are being pickled with their leaves, טהורות,
Tehoros, they're טהורות. Tehoros. ואמר, Ve-amar, so he said: הוויות דרב ושמואל
קחזינא הכא. Havayah de-Rav ve-Shmuel kachazina hacha. I see here like there
are issues here like, oy, this is hurting my head, as he
essentially says. It's like the types of questions רב ושמואל, Rav ve-Shmuel,
רב ושמואל Rav ve-Shmuel were רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda rebbe, that רב
ושמואל's Rav ve-Shmuel discussions are implicit in this משנה, Mishnah, but basically
it means like I can't even figure out what's going on. This
seems to me to raise issues that I know רב ושמואל Rav
ve-Shmuel would go to town on, but I'm lost. Okay, that's what
he's saying. So he didn't really, now by the way, this is
a debate of exactly what between רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos what
this משנה Mishnah does mean. רש"י Rashi says what it means is
that because you are normally a leaf of something, like a leaf
of an olive, is considered like a שומר shomer or a יד,
yad, a protector or an indirect way of moving the olive, so
if something טמא tamei touches it, the טומאה tumah transfers to the
olive because it's considered like an extension of the olive. But if
you're pickling it, then the leaves are going to wilt and wither
and therefore they don't have their status. תוספות Tosafos says that's not
what's going on here, what's going on here is whether the leaves
themselves are considered to be food or not, because maybe they can
be pickled, maybe they could be eaten or not. And the basic
point here is that in these contexts where they're being pickled, they're
not edible and therefore the leaves on their own terms are not
food. So anyway, just interesting to note that, look, already just פשט
pshat of this משנה Mishnah is already debated by רש"י Rashi and
תוספות. Tosafos. So clearly רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says I don't know
what's going on here. ואילו, Ve-ilu,
that's what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said, ואנן, ve-anan, and when it
comes to us, says רב פפא Rav Pappa to אביי, Abaye, קא
מתנינן בעוקצין תליסר מתיבתא. kamasnina be-Uktzin tleser masifta.
We have 13 different
approaches to learning the מסכתא masechet of עוקצין. Uktzin. So,
or 13 ישיבות, yeshivos, this could be what it means, like 13
different ישיבות yeshivos are learning it, but רש"י Rashi says 13 different
approaches to learning it. Clearly we're bigger תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim than
they were. But nevertheless, miracles happened to them but didn't happen to
us. What does that mean?
So he says, ואילו רב יהודה, ve-ilu Rav Yehuda, when רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda כי הוה שלף חד מסאניה, אתא מיטרא. ki havei shalif
chad mesana, ata mitra. He would just take off one shoe when
they were having a public תענית ta'anis to bring rain, and they
would take off their shoes like we do
on תשעה באב Tisha B'av and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Take off
their shoe, all he would do is he would remove the first
shoe and all of a sudden it would start raining. He just
had to start doing the תענית ta'anis and it would start raining.
Okay, ואנן, ve-anan, and we, קא מצערינן נפשין, kamesarina nafshin, we cause
great affliction to ourselves in terms of fasting, ומצוח קא צוחינן, u-mitzavcha
katzavchina, and we're crying out to God, וליכא דמשגח בן, ve-leika de-mashgach
ban, nobody's paying attention to us. So we're seeing, which is a
profound statement, we could be huge תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim but we
seem to be more distant from God. Okay, so what's the explanation
of that? Which by the way the גמרא Gemara recently mentioned חוני
המעגל, Choni Ha-Ma'agel, an interesting example, whoever heard of חוני המעגל Choni
Ha-Ma'agel ever saying a halachic statement, right?
He wasn't known for חוני המעגל, Choni Ha-Ma'agel, I think we're clear.
I understand, but the point is the sense of who is sort
of a חסיד chasid and close to God and whatever is acknowledged
is not always the same answer as who's the biggest תלמיד חכם.
Talmid Chacham. Okay, that's the question. By the way, I'm not sure
you're going to like the answer. Let's see what the answer is.
Already in there, okay. So
you'll see how it ties in in a minute. So far we
don't see how it ties in. Okay, anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei,
he said to him, קמאי הוו קא מסרי נפשייהו אקדושת השם. kamai
havei kamsrin nafshaihu a-kdushas Hashem.
This is how it ties in. The early ones would actually risk
themselves, anyway would sort of sacrifice themselves for the sake of defending
God's honor, for קידוש השם. Kiddush Hashem. Okay, it gets into this
idea of defending God's honor, which was the theme before. Okay. How
would they do this? ואנן לא מסרינן נפשין אקידוש השם V'anan lo
masrinei nafshan akiddush Hashem and we don't, we're not willing to take
risks and to sacrifice or risk ourselves when it comes to defending
God's honor. What's the example? He had רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav
Adda bar Ahava, here's an example like רב אדא בר אהבה—he's Rav
Adda bar Ahava
a later
אמורא—I Amora know, yeah, but it's an example of what you should
be doing, not of what you shouldn't be doing. Okay. חזייא לההיא
כותית דהות לבישא כרבלתא בשוקא. Chazya l'hahi Kutit d'hava l'visha karbalta beshuka.
He saw a certain Samaritan woman who was wearing a כרבלתא, karbalta,
which רש"י Rashi says is a certain garment. I don't know,
does Steinsaltz say what a כרבלתא karbalta is?
Yes, it's a bit of wool over woven.
Aha, okay, so this is, I was suspicious, I was suspecting that,
because I want you to look at what רש"י Rashi says, because
this is going to be a fascinating choice, especially
as relating to contemporary issues.
So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י?
Rashi?
כרבלתא karbalta רש"י Rashi just says שם לבוש חשוב, Shem l'vush chashuv,
okay,
some type of an important garment. Doesn't mention any שעטנז sha'atnez problems
or whatever. If you look at the side though, the מסורת הש"ס,
Mesoret HaShas, I don't know if you have it in your right-hand
column, פירש בגד אדום שאין דרך בנות ישראל להתכסות בו שהוא פריצות
ומביא לידי הרהור. Peirash beged adom she'ein derech b'not Yisrael l'hitkasot bo
shehu pritzut u'meivi lidei hirhur.
So the ערוך Aruch says they were wearing some type of a
red,
seductive garment, some type of an eye-catching garment, which frames the concern
in a very different way. So let's see what he did, I
think he probably anticipated. Exactly. סבר דבת ישראל היא. Savar d'bat Yisrael
hi. He figured, oh, this must be a Jewish woman and here
she's wearing this offensive כרבלתא. karbalta. So what is he going to
do? קם קרעיה מינה. Kam k'rayia mina. He got up,
he ripped it off of her. So you were asking before about
what if it's a woman, he ripped it off of her. איגלאי
מילתא דכותית היא. Iglaei milta d'Kutit hi. Turned out she was a
non-Jew, she was a Samaritan or non-Jewish woman. Why bother? So שיימוה
בארבע מאה זוזי. Shaimuha b'arba me'ah zuzei.
So they said he owed her 400 זוז, zuz, maybe for the
cost of the dress, maybe also for the embarrassment. Actually, there's an
interesting whole discussion anyway, also there's a whole discussion though about בושת
boshet and embarrassment that in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Anyway, he had
to pay 400 זוז zuz for this offense. אמר לה מה שמך.
Amar lah mah sh'meich. He said to her, what's your name? אמרה
ליה מטון. Amrah lei Maton. She said to him, מטון. Maton. My
name is מטון, Maton, Nathan, I don't know. אמר לה מטון מטון
ארבע מאה זוזי שויא. Amar lah Maton Maton arba me'ah zuzei shavya.
So מטון Maton is Aramaic for מאתיים, matayim, 200. So מטון מטון,
Maton Maton, 200 200, it cost me 400 זוז. zuz. So you
see he was מוסר moser himself for קידוש השם. kiddush Hashem. Too
bad we don't do that. Now,
I know. So the question is,
what—so, exactly. The question is, what was he doing ripping off her
clothes? What did he think it was about? Now the most obvious
thing to say, and I'm curious to see what Steinsaltz's
evidence is,
but the most obvious thing to say is in the context of
ripping off your clothes before, it was about שעטנז, sha'atnez, right? Where
basically it is that אין עצה ואין תבונה לנגד השם. Ein eitzah
v'ein tevunah l'neged Hashem. You can't violate whatever, I'm going to rip
it off. Now of course that gets to my earlier question. Here's
a person that's
oblivious and you're not just informing them and giving them the option
to take it off, you're doing it yourself and they're בשוגג, beshogeg,
they're not במזיד. bemezid. But still, in the context of the earlier
discussion, the לנגד השם neged Hashem is protecting God's honor if somebody's
walking around wearing שעטנז, sha'atnez, I'm going to intervene. Now it also
says, the same way you don't care about כבוד הרב, kavod harav,
you don't care about the fact that this woman's going to be
walking around naked, okay, and so on. But that is at least
what it's saying in context. The ערוך Aruch's explanation is a very
dangerous one in the sense that it basically treats it directly into
what's going on nowadays, that people see women dressed in ways that's
immodest, and it's the women's fault and they're the ones to blame
and whatever, and the other problem of course is that the action
then is he strips her naked. So it's hard to read this
as though the problem is that in her current state she's
leading to men's illicit thoughts because by ripping off the dress you're
only going to make it worse. Right. So, anyway, but that is
the way the ערוך Aruch reads it and that then
has—what about embarrassing somebody? Well, then the point is אין עצה ואין
תבונה לנגד השם, Ein eitzah v'ein tevunah l'neged Hashem, that's the way
they'll read this. Right. And the תוספות Tosafot says
this is why they had ניסים, nissim, they were so full, right,
right.
So even if—so that's the other point to make, which is, right,
that is the other point to make, that even if you say
it's about the שעטנז sha'atnez case and not about the case
like specifically about men controlling women's bodies and you're not צנועה tznuah
and that's your problem whatever, it's still a problem, right? Because this
is being held up as some amazing thing, why they had miracles
occur to them, and it's still you go and you're ripping clothes
off of people. I don't care if it's a man or it's
a woman. You go and you tell the person, maybe like we
said before, maybe they're בשוגג, beshogeg, maybe you don't even have to
tell them, but
still praising a certain type of fanaticism. I will say though, it's
not like here's another
mistake people make. They say, oh look,
I wrote an op-ed about this whole issue of men and צניעות
tzniut and women's bodies whatever. Oh, what about this גמרא? Gemara? So
besides it's just the ערוך, Aruch, but the other point is It’s
also,
this is אביי's Abaye response to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. It was
one person’s take on this question: why did the early ones have
these miracles occur to them? You don’t have to universalize it as
the גמרא Gemara says this is the right
behavior. People tend to lose the fact that the גמרות Gemaras have
many different voices and opinions in them anyway, however we explain what’s
going on here, it was אביי's Abaye response to רב פפא. Rav
Pappa. Yes. This
is true, it does end with that without a comment.
Yeah. They had miracles because they needed miracles. The later generations didn’t
need them because they were more
careful. And second...
but that’s why the later generations had problems with
rains because I don’t get that.
But the other interesting thing is they mention that the early generation
was expert in נזיקין, Nezikin, which we’re actually not that good about
today.
Alright, yes.
Let me just ask this question. One is when these people are
talking
it seems like a lack of humility about who they are.
What do you mean? It’s the opposite. He says, why did no...
oh you mean because first he says we know so much more
תורה?
Torah? We deserve... why would we deserve... after all we’ve done... we’re
more learned
and this...
Yeah, well that gets to a question about humility and honesty with
yourself, meaning it’s one thing to objectively know what you know and
what you don’t know, it’s another thing to
say like
גאוה ga'avah has more of like what’s coming to me and
how thinking that what you did
is...
That’s a larger discussion about the difference between being humble does not
mean being dishonest with yourself about your accomplishments. Okay. But it is
a point well taken and I guess it’s also a point taken
about the issue of the flip, the issue of
כבוד הרב, kevod harav, Rachel, as the other day,
about whether you’re allowed to assume that other rabbis made mistakes or
whatever. Here, I don’t think it’s an issue of כבוד הרב kevod
harav to say that the earlier generations didn’t know as much תורה
Torah as we did. Nowadays you try to say that, somebody would
take you out and say, how dare you not have that type
of respect for that great rabbi. So the גמרא Gemara clearly didn’t
feel that that assessment was an issue of כבוד הרב, kevod harav,
it was just an objective honest assessment. Yeah, Rachel.
What’s the train of thought of the גמרא? Gemara? Yes. I just
don’t... can you
just summarize?
The train of thought is you strip כלאים kilayim off of your
own garment because you’d rather protect God’s honor of not violating the
commandment than your own honor. That’s good, but you stripped it off
of yourself. And now, reading it that this is a שעטנז shatnez
garment, which is I think the פשט pshat reading, and now, if
you're really defending God’s honor, you won’t only strip it off of
yourself, you’ll strip off those כלאים kilayim garments from other people who
are wearing them. And that’s why the early generations had miracles done
to them because they were willing to get themselves lose money and
shamed and mocked and beaten up by people because they were going
to go out and be קנאים kana'im and strip those garments off
of other people as well.
It’s about God’s honor being more important than humans’.
Right. And that’s why even reading it about שעטנז, shatnez, the upshot
is not great, because it’s one thing to say I shouldn’t be
concerned about my own dignity, I should rather expose myself than do
an עבירה, aveirah, okay, it’s a very different thing than I should
go out and take this innocent person who’s not even willfully violating
and essentially do like some act of פנחס Pinchas and go ahead
and strip it in order to protect... it’s an act of... like
a פנחס Pinchas type of an act of being מקנא להשם, mekane
l'Hashem, right, but you’re doing it for this person who’s not willingly
violating.
Yes, I just wanted to suggest by way of listening to the
triple point and when he's saying some patients...
I was thinking about that too. If I was only more patient
I would have asked you about it, that had occurred to me
as well. How do you know by the... what?
If she was Jewish it would have been okay. Right, the only
thing...
exactly,
exactly, exactly. Alright, I think we really have to...
anyway, some of the גמרות Gemaras come to the exact opposite conclusion,
to say this is one voice.
So, yeah, I’d have to try to find it, but if I
can find a clear... okay, let’s go on. רב גידל Rav Gidel
הוה רגיל דהוה קאזיל ויתיב אשערי דטבילה.
hava ragil dahava ka'azil veyasiv
asha'arei detvilla. Now here we hear, okay, interesting because we're dealing with
men and women issues, so let’s take a look. רב גידל Rav
Gidel used to sit by the gates of the טבילה, tvilla, of
the access to the מקוה. mikveh. אמר להו, Amar lehu, הכי טבילו
והכי טבילו. hachi tivilu vehachi tivilu. And he said to the women,
be sure when you go down
there
that you do the טבילה tvilla this way and that way, be
sure to duck your head in or pay attention to this. Anyway,
he was giving them advice as they were going in, maybe even
he was overseeing it, I hope not, but anyway, אמרו ליה רבנן,
amru lei rabanan, rabbis said to him, לא קא מסתפי מר מיצר
הרע? lo ka mistafi mar mi'yeitzer hara? Aren't you afraid of your
evil inclination about the fact that you're talking to these women right
before they're going to the מקוה mikveh and that sort
of... flaming your lustful desires? אמר להו, Amar Lehu, he said to
them, דמיין באפי כי קקי חיורי, Damyan be-appai ki kaki chivri, oh
to me they're all white ducks. I don't know, they don't mean
anything to me. I don't pay attention to these types of things.
I don't believe that! Yeah, exactly. Now, ר' יוחנן R' Yochanan הוה
רגיל דהוה קאזיל ויתיב אשערי דטבילה. hava ragil de-hava ka-azil ve-yasiv asha'arei
d'tevilah. Now
ר' יוחנן R' Yochanan used to sit by the gates of the
מקוה. mikvah. אמרי, Amri, he wouldn't talk to the women, he would
just sit there. I'll get back in a second. אמרי, Amri, כי
סלקן בנות ישראל ואתיין מטבילה, ki salkan benot Yisrael ve-asyan mi-tevilah, when
they come up and having left the מקוה, mikvah, מסתכלן בי, mistaklan
bi, they'll look at me as they're leaving the מקוה, mikvah, ונהוי
להו זרע דשפיר כוותי, ve-nehavei lehu zara de-shapiri kevasi, and they will
have children as beautiful as I. There was definitely a very strong
belief in... of course. Yes, well that's true. There was definitely a
strong belief amongst the rabbis that
that the child, the way the child would turn out was a
function of what the man and the wife were thinking and doing
at the moment of conception. And that would impact the nature of
the kids. And that leads to another גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim
talking about if they're doing certain sexual violations or improper sort of
types of activities during sex that that leads to children having certain
deformities, and if they're thinking about certain things then the kids turn
out based on what they're thinking. This was a very prevalent belief.
So here he's saying they're looking at me, then understand what he's
saying, they're going to have sex with their husbands but they'll be
thinking about me and therefore lead to the kids turning out to
be beautiful. Now we know from the previous story that ר' יוחנן
R' Yochanan was beautiful, but still it's a little bit besides you
know it's a little bit funny that here he's hoping they're thinking
about him. Maybe it'll just be in the background and it won't
be in the foreground of their mind but it will be something
that they're thinking about. But anyway, yes, it does raise a lot
of fascinating questions. Anyway, so let's see.
Sitting and watching women going into מקוה mikvah was...
maybe he wasn't looking. Maybe he wasn't looking. He was just there
to be looked at, not to look. Okay. By the way, in
that context, I don't know if you read about two weeks ago
tying into this whole issue of צניעות tzniut and men dictating for
women's bodies, I read that this, I think this was in הארץ
Haaretz or somewhere, there was a post that they recently started selling
in ישראל Yisrael and it was a very hot item, glasses for
חרדים Chareidim that actually blur vision beyond like a few feet in
front of you. So that they can wear it so they don't
have to see how other people are dressed and see. Yes. And
so ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, it's much better than the alternative. Anyway,
we'll never find shot.
All right.
So, אמרו ליה
רבנן,
Amru
leh Rabbanan, so the rabbis said to him, לא קא מסתפי מר
מעינא בישא? Lo ka-mistafei mar mi-ayina bisha? Are you not afraid about...
are you not afraid about the עין הרע, Ayin Hara, meaning not
maybe... no, the other thing is you were talking to the women,
you were looking at the women which is... let me talk. Yes,
עין בישא. Ayin Bisha. Okay, it's the translation right there. The first
case is you were talking to the women, not ר' יוחנן, R'
Yochanan, the other one, and they were afraid that talking and interacting
with them, you know, is fans the flames of the יצר הרע.
Yetzer Hara. Here he's just sitting, he's learning his גמרא, Gemara, he's
doing this. He's not looking at the women as they're going to
the מקוה. mikvah. But all the women are looking at him and
the goal is for them to... oh look at this gorgeous rabbi,
look at this handsome guy, so that leads to עין הרע. Ayin
Hara. Everybody's paying attention to how good-looking you are. So are you
afraid of that? So he says, אמר להו, Amar Lehu, he says,
אנא מזרעא דיוסף קאתינא. Ana mi-zara de-Yosef ka-asina. No, I'm from the
descendants of יוסף. Yosef. דלא שלטא ביה עינא בישא, de-la shalta beh
ayina bisha, the descendants of יוסף Yosef are protected from עין הרע.
Ayin Hara. דכתיב בן פורת יוסף בן פורת עלי עין, de-chtiv ben
porat Yosef ben porat alei ayin,
like a fruitful child is יוסף, Yosef, fruitful child עלי עין. alei
ayin. So what does עלי עין alei ayin mean? So the גמרא
Gemara says, ואמר רבי אבהו אל תקרי עלי עין אלא עולי עין,
Ve-amar Rabbi Abbahu al tikrei alei ayin ela olei ayin, like you
rise up above the עין הרע. Ayin Hara. רב יוסי ברבי חנינא
אמר מהכא, Rav Yossi berebi Chanina amar me-hacha, וידגו לרוב בקרב הארץ,
ve-yidgu la-rov be-kerev ha-aretz,
the ברכה bracha that יעקב Yaakov gives to the children of יוסף,
Yosef, they should like swarm for the for many in the midst
of the land, but the word is דג, dag, like a fish.
מה דגים שבים מים מכסים עליהם ואין עין הרע שולטת בהן, mah
dagim she-ba-yam mayim mechasim aleihem ve-ein ayin hara sholetet bahen, the same
way fish in the ocean water covers over them and there's... since
there's no עין הרע Ayin Hara on the fish, ואין עין הרע
שולטת בהן, ve-ein ayin hara sholetet bahen, there's no עין הרע Ayin
Hara on them, אף זרעו של יוסף אין עין הרע שולטת בהן,
af zaro shel Yosef ein ayin hara sholetet bahen, even the seed
of יוסף Yosef there is no עין הרע Ayin Hara around that
is on them. That's why you know Tuesday is יום שהוכפל בו
כי טוב, yom she-huchpal bo ki tov, right? Because...
is that right? No.
What? Well... oh for the... yeah, yeah, yeah. No, but okay, forget
that. Okay.
No, that's... I mean whatever, fine. Forget that. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, ואיבעית אימא עין שלא רצתה לזון ממה שאינו שלו אין
עין הרע שולטת בו, ve-iba'is eima ayin she-lo ratzah la-zun mi-mah she-eino
shelo ein ayin hara sholetet bo, so an eye that did not
want to... that יוסף Yosef that did not want to take something
that wasn't his, he wasn't אשת פוטיפר, Eshet Potiphar, again you know
using it as a food metaphor, אין עין הרע שולטת בו. ein
ayin hara sholetet bo. So because the עין הרע Ayin Hara is
basically about people being jealous and you know sort of saying, why
does he get to be so good-looking? Why don't I get to
be so good-looking? And that sort of sense of jealousy ultimately is
what the עין הרע Ayin Hara is about. So since יוסף Yosef
was not desirous and coveting something that wasn't his, that somehow protects
him.
Isn't he the one that lost ten children, but what he said
before or after that?
רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. That's an interesting fact.
Right.
That's interesting. I thought you were going to ask another question, which
is how does he know the עין הרע Ayin Hara wasn't שולט
בו? sholet bo? Maybe that's why he lost his ten kids, you
know? But but
yeah.
But anyway, but this גמרא Gemara besides this issue about, you know,
it's again, it's obviously this issue about, you know, wanting women to
think about him when they're going to have sex with their husbands,
you know, because especially because the גמרא Gemara I should say, in
נדרים, Nedarim, that's the גמרא Gemara I alluded to, that talks about
proper sexual behavior between husband and wife, the end of that גמרא
Gemara basically says that it's not really about what you're doing, it's
about how you're relating to one another and says the real one
of the real problems is that you're thinking about somebody else, well
talking to the man, you're thinking about another woman when you're having
sex with your wife. But you know here, the גמרא Gemara doesn't
seem to be so bothered by the fact that they'll have looked
at him and maybe think of him, maybe they're not preoccupied with
him or whatever, but anyway that's one thing. But the other thing
also, you know, I should say that although this issue that I
can talk to the women, I won't have, I won't be misled,
they're like white geese and so on, you know, it's like, you
know, whether you are skeptical or not skeptical, that that actually does
become an important principle about that some issues that relate to interaction
of sexes are contextual. So when it comes to certain questions of
like, you know, shaking hands and certain types of activities that are
not intrinsically problematic but are problematic because they could lead to sexual
thoughts, to what degree
does context matter? And this גמרא Gemara amongst others is very relevant
for the ראשונים Rishonim and the פוסקים Poskim to say some of
these issues about whether these are prohibited or non-prohibited activities that aren't
objectively prohibited, it depends on the context of whether they lead to
sexual thoughts or not and that this becomes an important גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah, it's even exactly that. One was, and I forget where it
is, it's a גמרא Gemara that one of the rabbis was מרכיב
markiv the כלה kallah on his shoulder, right? יא, כתובות, Ya, Ketubot,
that's right. And then the other one was, I just thought it
was interesting that he took this פסוק pasuk of בן פורת יוסף
בן פורת עלי עין, Ben Porat Yosef ben porat alei ayin, because
the end of it is בנות צעדה עלי שור. banot tzada alei
shur. It's the women are going up to look at you.
But that's why it's not a problem that they're looking.
No, I know,
but I mean it's also echoing the idea of women looking at
רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. That's the point. Okay, now so that was
a fascinating גמרא. Gemara. Now we move on to another very critical
גמרא, Gemara, not about, we're moving away from the issue about the
burying of the dead and the issues that that raised, the חברה
קדישא, Chevra Kadisha, and then these fascinating digressions in the גמרא Gemara
to another discussion about who is obligated in various of the מצוות
mitzvot that we are talking about. So let's take a look. נשים
ועבדים וקטנים פטורין מקריאת שמע. Nashim va'avadim u'ketanim peturin mikriat shema. Women,
slaves and children, a classic trio,
non-free male adults, right, are exempt from קריאת שמע. Kriat Shema. Why?
Because קריאת שמע Kriat Shema is a time-bound מצוה mitzvah and therefore
women are exempt from מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvot asei shehazman grama.
Slaves have the same obligation as women. Children is an interesting discussion
because we say that actually children when they get to the age
of חינוך chinuch are obligated, at least the parents are obligated to
teach them, father obligated to teach him קריאת שמע, Kriat Shema, but
and that leads into the whole discussion in רש"י Rashi תוספות, Tosafot,
are we talking about above the age of חינוך, chinuch, below the
age of חינוך. chinuch. It might also be saying that the children
are exempt, the father might have an obligation to train them, but
the children themselves don't have an immediate obligation. Okay, so these are
time-bound מצוות. mitzvot. They're exempt from קריאת שמע. Kriat Shema. ומן התפילין,
u'min ha'tefillin, and from תפילין. tefillin. We know they're exempt from תפילין
tefillin is a דרשה drasha because we first assume that they're exempt
from תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, ולימדתם אותם את בניכם, v'limadetem otam et
bneichem, ולא בנותיכם, v'lo bnoteichem, which, you know, again is not explicit,
obviously you could have read בניכם bneichem as gender-neutral, but we first
start with that, that there's not a מצוה mitzvah of תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah for women, and then we say that leads to וקשרתם
לאות על ידכם, ukshartam l'ot al yedchem, that you bind it as
a sign on your hand, so if women are exempt from תורה,
Torah, they're exempt from תפילין. tefillin. The other point could be also
that תפילין tefillin are time-bound if תפילין tefillin don't apply at night,
but that's debated. Okay, so now it says
וחייבין בתפילה, vechayavin bitfila, they're obligated in תפילה, tefilla, well you might
have considered that to be time-bound, ובמזוזה, uvimzuza, and by a מזוזה
mezuza because מזוזה mezuza is certainly not time-bound and it's on the
house and it's regular and whatever, ובברכת המזון, uvirkat hamazon, and ברכת
המזון. Birkat Hamazon. Now that's interesting in a way, it's not time-bound,
it's not linked to a particular time, but it is like not
a, you know,
it's a periodic one, it's only when you eat. But we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara that this, but the גמרא Gemara does not
seem that doesn't make it time-bound and so to that says women
are obligated. But we'll see all about this inside. Let's read a
little גמרא. Gemara. קריאת שמע. Kriat Shema. So let's talk about their
exemption from שמע. Shema. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא הוא.
Mitzvat asei shehazman grama hu. It's a time-bound
מצוה. mitzvah. וכל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות. Vechol mitzvat asei
shehazman grama nashim peturot. Women are exempt. Now this is a principle
in קידושין, Kiddushin, but it should be said that there's about as
many, the רמב"ם Rambam already says in פירוש המשניות, Perush Hamishnayot, there
are about as many exceptions to the rule as there are cases
that apply to the rule, in both directions. There are things that
are time-bound that women are obligated in, there are things that are
not time-bound that women are exempt from. So how much... this rule
really it tells me everything I need to know is very questionable.
So you could say פשיטא, Peshita, of course I know it, I
know the rule, but the rule itself is not such a such
a water-tight rule. Nevertheless, anyway the גמרא Gemara says if I know
that rule and this fits in the rule, why did you have
to tell it to me? So it says no. מהו דתימא mahu
deteima אימר דאתא הוא ולית בה מלכות שמים, eimar deata hu vleit
be malchut shamayim, maybe it's so central, statement's fundamentally of our faith?
So maybe it has מלכות שמים malchut shamayim and therefore women should
be obligated regardless, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan this is telling
us not. You also could have said what the גמרא Gemara is
going to get at maybe if the although it does apply morning
and night, since the morning and night is a sense of like
throughout your day, even though the way it's translated is certain hours
in the morning and certain hours in the night, maybe conceptually it's
an idea of constantly, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't go there. The
גמרא Gemara does just say I would have thought מלכות שמים malchut
shamayim and in the end we tell me that none of those
things are true, presumably we apply the standard rule of time-bound מצווה
mitzvah and say women are exempt.
Yes, you used to think that כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot had an
override, like override here
or in the previous סוגיא, sugya, yeah,
right, but מלכות שמים malchut shamayim does.
כבוד הבריות Kevod habriyot overrides,
there was a discussion, the earlier discussion was that כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot can override potentially certain other obligations in a situation, right, but
מלכות שמים malchut shamayim doesn't.
Well, nobody is preventing women from saying the שמע, Shema, the question
is of to create an obligation, so it's not exactly analogous. What
I thought you were going to say was that כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot we should note in the previous סוגיא sugya also overwrote saying
of the שמע Shema which has the מלכות שמים malchut shamayim in
it, which goes again to the weight of the כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot and the כבוד המת. kevod hamet. Okay, anyways now the גמרא
Gemara continues, ומיני תפילין, umini tefillin, and they don't wear תפילין, tefillin,
פשיטא, peshita, obviously. Now why is it obvious?
So let's see anyway what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. It doesn't
tell us why it's obvious, no. מהו דתימא mahu deteima הואיל ואיתקש
למזוזה, hoil veitkesh lemezuza, connected to מזוזה, mezuza, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that that doesn't matter, it's a תפילין tefillin are either
because תפילין tefillin are time-bound, or it might
because it's connected to the מצווה mitzvah of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah.
Now, then it says וחייבת במזוזה, vechayevet bemezuza, right? Yeah, they're obligated
in מזוזה. mezuza. Now רש"י, Rashi, the גירסא girsa apparently original גירסא
girsa was פשיטא, peshita, of course they're obligated in תפילה, tefilla, because
it's, well anyway let's just read our version, it says דרחמי נינהו.
derachamei ninhu. Why? Because they are רחמים, rachamim, now this is important
which we'll get to particularly in the next פרק. perek. רחמים Rachamim
literally means compassion and it sort of means it's a beseeching of
God for compassion, but it also really refers to the fact that
it's sort of like our pouring out of our own feelings and
רחמים rachamim is the key word in the גמרא, Gemara, it's a
technical word which emphasizes the non-formalistic aspect of prayer. It's actually to
some degree in contrast to when it says it talks about תפילה
tefilla being כנגד קרבנות. keneged korbanot. The concept of כנגד קרבנות keneged
korbanot which is all about the formal obligations of prayer is רחמי
נינהו rachamei ninhu is like the personal prayer that emerges from within.
And the point, and we'll see this later, but the basic principle
of the גמרא Gemara is that that is the foundation of prayer
even if it gets laid upon it the rabbinic and the formalistic
structures. At its core it is this very personal experience that comes
from within. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says that's why they're obligated
in prayer, because although there are specific times for prayer, right? At
its core it is not about this time and that time and
שהזמן גרמא, shehazman grama, it is about the personal need to turn
to God which is really universal and at all times. So that's
you know, that, some people read it differently, women also need God's
רחמים, rachamim, so they need the results of the prayer, but I
think it's a more statement about the fundamental nature of prayer is
not about its formal structure. So the גמרא Gemara says nevertheless מהו
דתימא mahu deteima אימא הואיל וכתיב בה eima hoil uchtiv ba ערב
ובוקר וצהרים erev vavoker vetzahorayim למצות עשה שהזמן גרמא דמי. lemitzvot asseh
shehazman grama dami. It basically means since it is morning, evening, and
night, it is like a time-bound מצווה, mitzvah, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan not. Even that הוה אמינא hava amina is fascinating because
what is, why quote the פסוק? pasuk? I would have thought because
there's a הלכה halacha of morning, afternoon, and night. But again what
it seems to be saying is even from within your argument that
it's about this sort of basic religious human experience and not about
the formal structure, but maybe even that experience is linked to different
times. There's a, people normally experience a need to pray morning and
a separate need to pray in the afternoon, so maybe even that
sort of human religious experience is somewhat time-bound. It says no, the
human religious experience fundamentally transcends issues of time and therefore it is
not limited to, it applies equally to women as to men. Okay,
let's read a little more. So the גמרא Gemara says that's that,
וממזוזה, umimezuza, מזוזה, mezuza, פשיטא, peshita, obviously they're obligated in
מזוזה, mezuza, because why should they not be? No, מהו דתימא mahu
deteima הואיל ואיתקש לתלמוד תורה, hoil veitkesh letalmud torah, it's connected to
תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, so the same way they're exempt from תפילין
tefillin they should be exempt from מזוזה, mezuza, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan not, that it's something that fundamentally is about sort of
the status of the house and so on and therefore they are
based on other ways we know that, that does not, it's not
true.
And how we know they're פטור patur from תלמוד תורה? Talmud Torah?
Because that's an alluding, referring to other גמרות Gemarot where we'd know
these things based on... ולמדתם אותם את בניכם ולא בנותיכם. v'limadetem otam
et bneichem v'lo bnoteichem. This גמרא Gemara is not expanding the whole
thing. It doesn't tell you why don't I say that, why don't
I say by מזוזה mezuzah the same thing I say by תפילין?
tefillin? It's not giving you the answer, it's just sort of giving
you the highlights about why it's important to say these things. Okay?
I just want to finish the two dots and make some comments.
ברכת המזון Birchat hamazon and בענטשן, Bentsching, פשיטא, peshita, obviously, that ברכת
המזון Birchat hamazon presumably takes it for granted that it's not considered
to be
time-bound. מהו דתימא mahu d'teima הא כתיב ha k'tiv בערב בשר לאכול
ולחם בבוקר לשבוע, b'erev basar l'echol v'lechem baboker lishboa, so again, similar
to I think what it was saying before about prayer, although you
can pray at all times, but sort of the natural rhythms of
life might be to pray three times. So the natural rhythms of
eating are morning and evening, so even if it's not in a
formal way time-bound, there's an aspect of it being time-bound in terms
of sort of the natural ways in which we eat. קמשמע לן,
Kamashmalan, so כמצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא דמי, k'mitzvot asei she'hazman grama dami,
so maybe that makes it like time-bound, קמשמע לן Kamashmalan not. Now
the גמרא Gemara is then going to go into ברכת המזון, Birchat
hamazon, so we'll have to pick up with that tomorrow, but I
want to just say a few things about this. Number one, you
know, this is a very important גמרא Gemara obviously about how you
conceptualize, like I said, the nature of תפילה. Tefila. What it means
when we say time-bound, time-bound in a formal way in terms of
the formal obligation, time-bound in the sort of sense of like, you
know, the rhythms of life, the rhythms of the human experience. We
sort of suggested the opposite by קריאת שמע. Kriyat Shema. We said
by קריאת שמע, Kriyat Shema, even though it is time-bound, I could
argue it's not if the fundamental concept is all the time. The
גמרא Gemara doesn't go that way. The other thing obviously is worth
noting about all of this is women's obligation in תפילה. Tefila. The
גמרא Gemara here does it with no qualifications. The sense is that
women are just as obligated as men. But the interesting question becomes,
you know, and the rabbinic תפילה Tefila is very time-bound, the biblical
תפילה, Tefila, though what the core experience is, is not. But so
are we splitting those? The simple sense of the גמרא Gemara is
no, since fundamentally the core aspect of תפילה Tefila is this doesn't
fall in this time-bound category, women are as obligated in תפילה Tefila
as men. And mostly pretty much all the ראשונים Rishonim and פוסקים
Poskim say that women are at least as obligated in שחרית Shacharit
and מנחה, Mincha, maybe not מעריב Maariv because מעריב Maariv has this
question of רשות, reshut, but certainly two תפילות Tefilot and maybe all
three, women are just as obligated as men. However, the practice for
hundreds of years were that women were like often illiterate and didn't
go to שול shul and their role, you know, was within the
home, sociologically speaking here, not halachically or anything, and the practice for
hundreds of years, women weren't really דאוונען, davening, you know, and saying
the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei.
They weren't saying שמונה עשרה?
Shemoneh Esrei? שמונה עשרה?
Shemoneh Esrei? Women pray?
No, they prayed their maybe private תחינות tchinot and prayers, whatever. You
clearly by reading the פוסקים, Poskim, I'm not saying in all places
at all times, but what happens is is that some פוסקים Poskim
look at this phenomenon and say how could we say women are
obligated? If you look around, women are not saying שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh
Esrei. And this תפילה Tefila means שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. And so
some say, okay, we have to start, you know, it's a problem
and we have to deal with it, but others make their peace
with it by trying to split this, if you would, the biblical
and the rabbinic. They say they're not obligated in the rabbinic formal
text two times a day, whatever, that is מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמה.
mitzvat asei she'hazman grama. They're obligated at this core experience of praying
sometime during the day, any words, any type of personal prayer, saying
מודה אני Modeh Ani would count, personal prayers would count and so
on. So that is like a post-facto way of dealing with the
phenomenon that people were not doing what it seems like they should
have been doing. But right now sociologically, I think it's more becoming
known in the Modern Orthodox communities that the simple reading of the
הלכה halacha is that women are obligated to דאוונען davening at least
two times a day, שחרית Shacharit and מנחה, Mincha, the שמונה עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. But many many people take it for granted, of course
women are פטור patur from תפילה, Tefila, you know, they'll take, you
know, exactly in opposite of this גמרא Gemara based on the widespread
phenomenon that women don't go, you know, to שול shul regularly during
weekdays and in many communities women don't דאוונען davening a regular שחרית
Shacharit and a מנחה. Mincha. So that, how these sociology and the
facts on the ground shapes perceptions, you know, and around these issues
of תפילה Tefila is very is fascinating.
Yeah, but women are obligated in שמע Shema but not because it's
a time-bound...
Women are not obligated in שמע. Shema. Right. Not at all.
Right, but you know, many of course do because of עול מלכות
שמים ol malchut shamayim and so on.
Prayer itself is to שמונה עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. תפילה Tefila in the גמרא Gemara means one thing: שמונה
עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Yes.
In the more right-wing communities, women דאוונען. davening. It's not they don't
דאוונען davening publicly, but they do דאוונען. davening. It's the Modern Orthodox
women that by and large don't bother with דאוונען. davening.
In the, you're telling me in the חרדי Chareidi communities women
שחרית Shacharit and מנחה, Mincha, they do?
Yes, they do. Aha, they do?
Privately, but my sister does. What?
That's fascinating because
I
will tell you that the פוסקים Poskim that are dealing with the
phenomenon of women not דאוונען davening was pre-Modern Orthodox. The women weren't
educated. Right.
And on and on. Could be. Could be.
Right, okay, I hear.
Right, okay,
one last comment by the way, which is רש"י Rashi had the
גירסא girsa when it says תפילה, Tefila, רש"י's Rashi the original גירסא
girsa was פשיטא, peshita, of course they're
obligated. Does the concept of time-boundedness as an exemption for women, is
it, do we apply it to Rabbinic מצוות *mitzvos* as well? רש"י
*Rashi* says, since תפילה *tefilla* is Rabbinic in the form that we
have it, the גמרא *Gemara* would not say, of course they're obligated,
it's not time-bound. The issue of time-bound and non-time-bound is not relevant
for Rabbinic מצוות *mitzvos*. That's what רש"י *Rashi* says. So he just
cut it out. And he just says the גמרא *Gemara* just says,
yeah, they're obligated because רחמי *rachamei*, but the discussion of time-bound is
irrelevant. תוספות *Tosfos* says no, actually the גרסה *girsa* is פשיטא *peshita*,
and the גמרא *Gemara* says פשיטא *peshita*, of course they're obligated, it
is not time-bound. And תוספות *Tosfos* says that even for Rabbinic מצוות
*mitzvos* we will often pattern them after biblical ones, and the issue
of time-boundedness and women's obligation could be relevant for Rabbinic מצוות *mitzvos*
as well. So although that hinges on to some degree on whether
you have this גרסה *girsa* of פשיטא *peshita*. Okay, I'll take the
rest after I just finish.